<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>
    
    <channel>
        <title>Multitouch Design</title>
        <atom:link href="http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        <link>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com</link>
        <description>Mobile design, development and delivery</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 21:53:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <language>en</language>
        <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
        <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
        <generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
        <cloud domain='multitouchdesign.wordpress.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
        <image>
            <url>http://s2.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</url>
            <title>Multitouch Design</title>
            <link>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com</link>
        </image>
        <atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="Multitouch Design" />
        <atom:link rel='hub' href='http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
        <item>
            <title>Booch and Rumbaugh</title>
            <link>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2013/03/13/booch-and-rumbaugh/</link>
            <comments>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2013/03/13/booch-and-rumbaugh/#comments</comments>
            <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 21:52:45 +0000</pubDate>
            <dc:creator>David Springgay</dc:creator>
            <category><![CDATA[Development]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Patterns]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Principles]]></category>
            
            <guid isPermaLink="false">http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/?p=507</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[The other day I was called into a meeting to discuss the requirements for a role we call Principal Engineer. There were about eight of us in the room. We each threw a few ideas on the table and within a few minutes the list was so long that I began to wonder if I&#8217;d [...]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=multitouchdesign.wordpress.com&#038;blog=20536839&#038;post=507&#038;subd=multitouchdesign&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The other day I was called into a meeting to discuss the requirements for a role we call Principal Engineer. There were about eight of us in the room. We each threw a few ideas on the table and within a few minutes the list was so long that I began to wonder if I&#8217;d pass through the interview process myself.</p>
            <p>After the meeting one idea stuck with me. We need someone who understands the &#8220;Fundamentals of Software Development&#8221;. Now, I&#8217;m not sure if there&#8217;s an official list of fundamentals, so I sat down with some of my old text books today to refresh my memory.</p>
            <p><a href="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2013/03/0805353402.jpg"> <img class="wp-image-527 alignleft" alt="0805353402" src="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2013/03/0805353402.jpg?w=254&#038;h=318" width="254" height="318" /></a><a href="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2013/03/128837.jpg"><img class="wp-image-528 alignnone" alt="128837" src="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2013/03/128837.jpg?w=224&#038;h=317" width="224" height="317" /></a></p>
            <p>I started out with a copy of <em>Object Oriented Design</em>, by Grady Booch. Booch starts his book by discussing the nature of software, or to be more precise, complexity. Complexity is a continual challenge in the development of large software systems. He describes a number of ways to bring order to chaos:</p>
            <ol>
            <li><span style="line-height:13px;"><em>Decomposition:</em> When designing a complex software system, it is essential to decompose it into smaller and smaller parts, each of which we may then refine independently. In order to understand any given level of the system, we need only comprehend a few parts (rather than all parts) at once.</span></li>
            <li><em>Abstraction:</em> We humans have an exceptionally powerful technique for dealing with complexity.  We abstract from it. Unable to master the entirety of a complex object, we chose to ignore the inessential details and deal instead with the generalized, ideal model of the object.</li>
            <li><em>Hierarchy:</em> Abstraction is a good thing, but in all except the most trivial applications we may find many more different abstractions than we can comprehend at one time. A set of abstractions often form a hierarchy, and by identifying these hierarchies in our design we greatly simplify our understanding of the problem.</li>
            <li><em>Encapsulation:</em> The abstraction of an object should precede the decisions about its implementation, and this should be hidden, or encapsulated from most clients. This encapsulation allows us to modify the implementation without affecting those clients.</li>
            </ol>
            <p>I also took a look at <em>Object Oriented Modeling and Design</em>, by James Rumbaugh and company. He points out that good programs do more than simply satisfy their functional requirements. Programs that follow proper design guidelines are more likely to be correct, reusable, extensible and quickly debugged.  Then he defines a set of object oriented style guidelines under the following categories:</p>
            <ol>
            <li>Reusability</li>
            <li>Extensibility</li>
            <li>Robustness</li>
            <li>Programming in the large. This refers to the creation of large software systems by large teams.</li>
            </ol>
            <p>He  goes on to define a number of rules for each category. Here&#8217;s a quick sample:</p>
            <ul>
            <li><em>Keep methods small:</em> If a method is large, break it into smaller methods. By breaking it into smaller parts, you may be able to reuse some parts. A method that exceeds one or two pages is probably too large.</li>
            <li><em>Separate policy and implementation:</em> Policy methods make decisions, and often vary from one application to the next. Implementation methods perform specific detailed operations, without deciding whether or why to do them. These are more likely to meaningful and reusable in other contexts.</li>
            <li><em>Provide uniform coverage:</em> If you write a method to get the last element of a list, write one to get the first element.</li>
            <li><em>Delegation:</em> Sometimes it appears that use of inheritance would increase code reuse within a program, when a true superclass/subclass relationship doesn&#8217;t exist.  Don&#8217;t give in to the temptation to use implementation inheritance. Use delegation instead.</li>
            <li><em>Encapsulate classes:</em> A class is encapsulated if its internal structure is hidden from other classes.  This makes it easier to change that implementation.</li>
            <li><em>Avoid case statements on object type:</em> Use methods instead. Case statements can be used to test internal attributes of an object, but should not be used to select behavior based on object type. Dispatching operations based on object type is the whole point of methods.</li>
            <li><em>Optimize after the program runs:</em> Often programmers spend too much effort trying to improve portions of the code that are infrequently executed. Measure the performance before optimizing it. You may be surprised to find that most parts consume little of the total time.</li>
            <li><em>Make methods readable:</em> It should be possible for someone other than the creator of the method to understand the code. This makes it easier to maintain or improve the code in the future.</li>
            <li><em>Choose names carefully:</em> There&#8217;s a reason programmers use a language. They need to communicate with the compiler and with other programmers. Make every name meaningful and correct.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>This is just a small sample from these books. They may be old, but the concepts they teach are just as valid today as they were when they were written.</p>
            <br />  <a rel="nofollow" href="http://feeds.wordpress.com/1.0/gocomments/multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/507/"><img alt="" border="0" src="http://feeds.wordpress.com/1.0/comments/multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/507/" /></a> <img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=multitouchdesign.wordpress.com&#038;blog=20536839&#038;post=507&#038;subd=multitouchdesign&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2013/03/13/booch-and-rumbaugh/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
            <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
            
            <media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/baaf3b5c536257b9132f368c3694a2b9?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">sprnggy</media:title>
            </media:content>
            
            <media:content url="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2013/03/0805353402.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">0805353402</media:title>
            </media:content>
            
            <media:content url="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2013/03/128837.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">128837</media:title>
            </media:content>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>You have to see it to believe it</title>
            <link>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/10/21/you-have-to-see-it-to-believe-it/</link>
            <comments>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/10/21/you-have-to-see-it-to-believe-it/#comments</comments>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Oct 2012 11:12:44 +0000</pubDate>
            <dc:creator>David Springgay</dc:creator>
            <category><![CDATA[Principles]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
            
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/?p=512</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[On my run this morning I listened to a pair of TED podcasts related to urban growth. In the first podcast Stewart Brand spoke about how 1 in 6 people on the planet are moving to or already living in urban shanty towns. For many of them, this will be an improvement upon rural, poverty [...]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=multitouchdesign.wordpress.com&#038;blog=20536839&#038;post=512&#038;subd=multitouchdesign&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On my run this morning I listened to a pair of TED podcasts related to urban growth. In the first podcast Stewart Brand spoke about how 1 in 6 people on the planet are moving to or already living in urban shanty towns. For many of them, this will be an improvement upon rural, poverty stricken subsistence. He believes that these peripheral areas will be a major source of development in the 21st century. In a related talk Robert Neuwirth calculated that by 2030 1 in 4 people will live in these shanty towns.</p>
            <p>As a software designer and developer I find this really intriguing. It&#8217;s easier to develop new technology if you truly understand the problem you are trying to solve, or if your own life is improved by that technology. The most interesting services and products for this shanty town market will probably come from those who live there.</p>
            <p>In many of these shanty towns there&#8217;s no running water, no electricity, and no access to sanitation or sewer systems. This sounds like a terrible setting, but Brand spoke about how these communities self organize. There is no unemployment. Everybody works. They run a food stall, a cafe, a bar, a hair dresser, a church, a school, clothes shops, copy centers, video stores (pirated), music stores (pirated), public transport, and more. They do this on their own, with little help from their government. It&#8217;s an unconventional economy.</p>
            <p><a href="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/dharavi-slums-001.jpg"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-518" title="Dharavi-slums-001" alt="" src="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/dharavi-slums-001.jpg?w=595"   /></a></p>
            <p>In London where I live there are approximately 10 million people, and public transport is an important service for everyone. I grew up in Canada, where public transport is often promoted as a green alternative, but in London the public transport system developed for a very different reason. In the 1800&#8242;s the London Underground was built to help middle class and wealthy citizens commute to work. They wanted to get out of the poverty stricken central areas of London. The poor people couldn&#8217;t afford it. Today public transport is a necessity for everyone. Many people live on the outskirts of London and commute to central London. If they all tried to commute by car there would be a huge traffic jam. It just wouldn&#8217;t work.</p>
            <p><a href="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/london-buses.jpg"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-519" title="WARNING:  PICTURE SCANNED FOR OVERNIGHT NEWSBuses" alt="" src="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/london-buses.jpg?w=595"   /></a></p>
            <p>London is an excellent place to build a business because there are 10 million customers and it&#8217;s the global center for finance and media. You can start a global brand or serve a global brand, such as Barclays, the Bank of America, HSBC, the BBC, Sky TV, News International, Virgin, British Airways or Samsung. It&#8217;s much easier to understand a market if your customer is just around the corner.</p>
            <p>In Canada the distance from one city to the next is much greater. The population density is very low, there are only a handful of large cities, and they are separated by hundreds or thousands of kilometers. In this situation, many Canadian companies focus on the US market first because it&#8217;s bigger than the Canadian market and easier to get to. This is made easier because the Canadian lifestyle is similar to an American lifestyle. We get each other.</p>
            <p><a href="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/canadian-prairies.jpg"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-520" title="canadian-prairies" alt="" src="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/canadian-prairies.jpg?w=595&#038;h=395" height="395" width="595" /></a></p>
            <p>The point is, if you want to design and sell good products into a market, you really need to understand what kind of problems the people in that market face. If you experience the same problems, your solution will be better. You need to go there, see the problems, and live the problems. Then new ideas will emerge.</p>
            <br />  <a rel="nofollow" href="http://feeds.wordpress.com/1.0/gocomments/multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/512/"><img alt="" border="0" src="http://feeds.wordpress.com/1.0/comments/multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/512/" /></a> <img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=multitouchdesign.wordpress.com&#038;blog=20536839&#038;post=512&#038;subd=multitouchdesign&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/10/21/you-have-to-see-it-to-believe-it/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
            <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
            
            <media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/baaf3b5c536257b9132f368c3694a2b9?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">sprnggy</media:title>
            </media:content>
            
            <media:content url="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/dharavi-slums-001.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">Dharavi-slums-001</media:title>
            </media:content>
            
            <media:content url="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/london-buses.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">WARNING:  PICTURE SCANNED FOR OVERNIGHT NEWSBuses</media:title>
            </media:content>
            
            <media:content url="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/canadian-prairies.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">canadian-prairies</media:title>
            </media:content>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>The Times and Times Literary Supplement</title>
            <link>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/09/20/the-times-and-times-literary-supplement/</link>
            <comments>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/09/20/the-times-and-times-literary-supplement/#comments</comments>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2012 14:20:35 +0000</pubDate>
            <dc:creator>David Springgay</dc:creator>
            <category><![CDATA[android]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Applications]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[android Times]]></category>
            
            <guid isPermaLink="false">http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/?p=499</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[It&#8217;s a red letter day. After working at News International for over a year, we have released the new version of the Times for Android, and the Times Literary Supplement.  There were days when I thought we&#8217;d never make it, but here we are: Install them for a 30 day preview. Send feedback. Help us [...]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=multitouchdesign.wordpress.com&#038;blog=20536839&#038;post=499&#038;subd=multitouchdesign&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s a red letter day. After working at News International for over a year, we have released the new version of the <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=uk.co.ni.times">Times</a> for Android, and the <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=uk.co.newsint.tls">Times Literary Supplement</a>.  There were days when I thought we&#8217;d never make it, but here we are:</p>
            <p><a href="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/09/thetimes.png"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-508" title="theTimes" src="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/09/thetimes.png?w=595" alt=""   /></a></p>
            <p>Install them for a 30 day preview. Send feedback. Help us improve them.</p>
            <br />  <a rel="nofollow" href="http://feeds.wordpress.com/1.0/gocomments/multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/499/"><img alt="" border="0" src="http://feeds.wordpress.com/1.0/comments/multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/499/" /></a> <img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=multitouchdesign.wordpress.com&#038;blog=20536839&#038;post=499&#038;subd=multitouchdesign&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/09/20/the-times-and-times-literary-supplement/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
            <slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
            
            <media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/baaf3b5c536257b9132f368c3694a2b9?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">sprnggy</media:title>
            </media:content>
            
            <media:content url="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/09/thetimes.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">theTimes</media:title>
            </media:content>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Titanium V PhoneGap</title>
            <link>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/05/17/titanium-v-phonegap/</link>
            <comments>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/05/17/titanium-v-phonegap/#comments</comments>
            <pubDate>Thu, 17 May 2012 08:24:33 +0000</pubDate>
            <dc:creator>David Springgay</dc:creator>
            <category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[PhoneGap Titanium]]></category>
            
            <guid isPermaLink="false">http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/?p=492</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[I spend a lot of time thinking about hybrid applications which employ web and native code. The following link provides great food for thought about Titanium and PhoneGap: Click here. Enjoy.<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=multitouchdesign.wordpress.com&#038;blog=20536839&#038;post=492&#038;subd=multitouchdesign&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I spend a lot of time thinking about hybrid applications which employ web and native code. The following link provides great food for thought about Titanium and PhoneGap:</p>
            <p><a title="Titanium v PhoneGap" href="http://developer.appcelerator.com/blog/2012/05/comparing-titanium-and-phonegap.html">Click here</a>.</p>
            <p>Enjoy.</p>
            <br />  <a rel="nofollow" href="http://feeds.wordpress.com/1.0/gocomments/multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/492/"><img alt="" border="0" src="http://feeds.wordpress.com/1.0/comments/multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/492/" /></a> <img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=multitouchdesign.wordpress.com&#038;blog=20536839&#038;post=492&#038;subd=multitouchdesign&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/05/17/titanium-v-phonegap/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
            <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
            
            <media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/baaf3b5c536257b9132f368c3694a2b9?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">sprnggy</media:title>
            </media:content>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Threading in Javascript</title>
            <link>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/04/30/threading-in-javascript/</link>
            <comments>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/04/30/threading-in-javascript/#comments</comments>
            <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2012 20:53:25 +0000</pubDate>
            <dc:creator>David Springgay</dc:creator>
            <category><![CDATA[android]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Development]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
            
            <guid isPermaLink="false">http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/?p=445</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[Over the past 6 months we&#8217;ve been developing a hybrid application for Android and iOS which uses a WebView to render news content. For those of you who are considering this approach, we&#8217;ve run into a challenge on Android worth noting. It doesn&#8217;t matter how many WebViews you create. They all share a single javascript [...]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=multitouchdesign.wordpress.com&#038;blog=20536839&#038;post=445&#038;subd=multitouchdesign&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Over the past 6 months we&#8217;ve been developing a hybrid application for Android and iOS which uses a WebView to render news content. For those of you who are considering this approach, we&#8217;ve run into a challenge on Android worth noting. It doesn&#8217;t matter how many WebViews you create. They all share a single javascript thread.</p>
            <p>In our application we have a view pager with three web views. We use this design to render an on screen article and two off screen articles. In order to render the content of an article, we run quite a bit of javascript code. This is the source of our challenge. In order to render an article off screen we have to run the same javascript. If this takes a long time, it will block any event handling code that we have in the on screen view. If this happens, user interface events can be ignored or processed after a delay. This results in an unresponsive user interface.</p>
            <p>In theory, we could address this problem by moving some of this work to a web worker (a background thread). However, the current Android WebView does not support web workers.</p>
            <p>It may be possible to perform some of the rendering computations in native code (ouch) or ahead of time on a server (yikes), but both of these represent a radical change. So we are currently looking for ways to improve the efficiency of our javascript code, or spread it out into time slices.</p>
            <p>In the future there may be a better solution. Google has recently released a <a title="Chrome for Android" href="http://arstechnica.com/gadgets/news/2012/02/chrome-finally-brings-modern-web-standards-to-android.ars">beta of Chrome for Android</a>. Chrome has first class support for web workers, web sockets, and remote debugging. The latter feature can be used to connect to and debug the code in a web view using a desktop debugger. Wouldn&#8217;t that be nice.</p>
            <p><a href="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/04/download.jpeg"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-493" title="download" src="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/04/download.jpeg?w=595" alt=""   /></a></p>
            <p>Unfortunately this solution will only help us when Chrome has been rolled out as a replacement for all of the old WebView code which already exists on Android 3.0 and above, or the market has moved on from Android 3.0. In a few years!</p>
            <br />  <a rel="nofollow" href="http://feeds.wordpress.com/1.0/gocomments/multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/445/"><img alt="" border="0" src="http://feeds.wordpress.com/1.0/comments/multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/445/" /></a> <img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=multitouchdesign.wordpress.com&#038;blog=20536839&#038;post=445&#038;subd=multitouchdesign&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/04/30/threading-in-javascript/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
            <slash:comments>5</slash:comments>
            
            <media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/baaf3b5c536257b9132f368c3694a2b9?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">sprnggy</media:title>
            </media:content>
            
            <media:content url="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/04/download.jpeg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">download</media:title>
            </media:content>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Sharing Information</title>
            <link>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/04/14/sharing-information/</link>
            <comments>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/04/14/sharing-information/#comments</comments>
            <pubDate>Sat, 14 Apr 2012 10:27:07 +0000</pubDate>
            <dc:creator>David Springgay</dc:creator>
            <category><![CDATA[Intellectual Property]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Patterns]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[social-media]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[technology]]></category>
            
            <guid isPermaLink="false">http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/?p=478</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[I recently read an opinion piece called Three Reasons Apple&#8217;s iCloud Isn&#8217;t Ready for Business, by Jonathan Blum. I&#8217;ve blogged about iCloud in the past. It&#8217;s a great way to access your own music, email, etc, on all of the Apple devices you own, but Jonathan&#8217;s piece made me realize that this isn&#8217;t sharing. Sharing [...]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=multitouchdesign.wordpress.com&#038;blog=20536839&#038;post=478&#038;subd=multitouchdesign&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I recently read an opinion piece called <a title="Not Ready for Business" href="http://www.entrepreneur.com/blog/222736">Three Reasons Apple&#8217;s iCloud Isn&#8217;t Ready for Business</a>, by Jonathan Blum. I&#8217;ve blogged about iCloud in the past. It&#8217;s a great way to access your own music, email, etc, on all of the Apple devices you own, but Jonathan&#8217;s piece made me realize that this isn&#8217;t sharing.</p>
            <p>Sharing is something you do with other people. When you share something with another person, you give them the right to read it, play it, or contribute to it. In contrast, the current incarnation of iCloud doesn&#8217;t support sharing. In fact, it protects the interests of Apple and the media industry by preventing you from sharing their content with other people.</p>
            <p>I don&#8217;t have any problems with this. It&#8217;s a reflection of the DRM bargain which Apple struck with the media industry when it built the iTunes Store. In the media industry there&#8217;s a growing desire to sell music, videos, news and information to paying customers over the internet. This is exemplified in the Apple iTunes Store, which operates a purchase based business model, and Spotify, which operates a rental based business model.</p>
            <p><a href="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/04/sharing1.jpg"><img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-484" title="sharing" src="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/04/sharing1.jpg?w=284&#038;h=300" alt="" width="284" height="300" /></a></p>
            <p>On the other hand, more and more of us are sharing the fruit of our own labor with others, and there are many ways to do it. You can use Drop Box, Google Docs, Facebook, Twitter, or Wikipedia, just to name a few. In each of these applications someone, an individual or a collective, is creating content and sharing it with others.</p>
            <p>These applications vary in the degree of privacy and control afforded to the author.  For instance, in Google Docs you can create a document and then share it with a select group of friends, if you want to.  In Facebook the sharing model is deliberately more public.  Everything you publish is shared with your friends, unless you go out of your way to keep it private. And in Twitter everything you tweet is immediately visible to the world. There&#8217;s no way to hide it. The kimono is open.</p>
            <p>The public nature of this information has led to a role reversal.  Whereas Apple and the traditional media industry operate by creating content and selling it to the people, Facebook and Wikipedia operate by harvesting the information which you and I create.  It&#8217;s a complex world where information is coming and going.</p>
            <br />  <a rel="nofollow" href="http://feeds.wordpress.com/1.0/gocomments/multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/478/"><img alt="" border="0" src="http://feeds.wordpress.com/1.0/comments/multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/478/" /></a> <img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=multitouchdesign.wordpress.com&#038;blog=20536839&#038;post=478&#038;subd=multitouchdesign&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/04/14/sharing-information/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
            <slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
            
            <media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/baaf3b5c536257b9132f368c3694a2b9?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">sprnggy</media:title>
            </media:content>
            
            <media:content url="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/04/sharing1.jpg?w=284" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">sharing</media:title>
            </media:content>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Redesigning MS Excel for a Tablet</title>
            <link>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/03/31/redesigning-ms-excel-for-a-tablet/</link>
            <comments>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/03/31/redesigning-ms-excel-for-a-tablet/#comments</comments>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Mar 2012 07:28:41 +0000</pubDate>
            <dc:creator>David Springgay</dc:creator>
            <category><![CDATA[android]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Applications]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Interaction]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Patterns]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
            
            <guid isPermaLink="false">http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/?p=448</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[If you took a popular desktop application and redesigned it for a tablet, what would it look like?  This is the question I asked myself about a week ago, when I started to redesign Microsoft Excel for a tablet. There are a number of things about a tablet which act as design forcing factors.  I&#8217;m [...]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=multitouchdesign.wordpress.com&#038;blog=20536839&#038;post=448&#038;subd=multitouchdesign&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you took a popular desktop application and redesigned it for a tablet, what would it look like?  This is the question I asked myself about a week ago, when I started to redesign Microsoft Excel for a tablet.</p>
            <p>There are a number of things about a tablet which act as design forcing factors.  I&#8217;m going to talk about three of them:</p>
            <ol>
            <li>Screen size</li>
            <li>Input mechanisms</li>
            <li>Platform widget design</li>
            </ol>
            <p>The <em>screen size</em> for a tablet is much smaller than a desktop computer screen, so it&#8217;s important to identify the key functions in an application.  If you include those features in the design, and ruthlessly exclude everything else, the application might just fit on the screen.</p>
            <p>The <em>primary input mechanism</em> for a tablet computer is your finger, or set of fingers.  A finger tip is much larger than a mouse pointer, so it&#8217;s important to ensure that every interactive element on the screen is easy to touch.  There usually isn&#8217;t a keyboard, so text entry will be performed using an on screen keyboard.  This takes up a lot of space, and reduces the visible document space even further.  And the accelerator keys which you have grown up with won&#8217;t really work, because once again, there may not be a keyboard.  This makes it more difficult to select multiple items with the shift key.  There is no shift key.</p>
            <p>Another factor to consider is <em>platform widget design</em>.  For instance, on most tablet computers, scrolling is performed directly.  There are no scroll bars.  You just touch an element and drag.  This is an important factor to consider when you need to support select, multi-select, reposition <em>and scroll</em>.</p>
            <p>With that in mind, let&#8217;s get started on the design.</p>
            <p>In order to determine the key features within MS Excel, I could go out and conduct a survey, collect tracking data from MS Excel, do some contextual inquiry, or analyse every document within an organisation. But no, I took a simpler approach. There are about half a dozen MS Excel documents on my computer. I took a look at the features which I use in each of those files.</p>
            <p>The key features which I use are as follows:</p>
            <ul>
            <li>I enter words, numbers, currency and date items into a table</li>
            <li>I cut, copy and paste items</li>
            <li>I frequently insert new rows and columns, and reorder these items.</li>
            <li>I write formulas using the &#8220;=&#8221; notation. These formulas often use arithmetic operators and the sum function. This is one of the really stellar things about Excel. You can create a functional computer program without even being a computer programmer.</li>
            <li>I use basic colour and text formatting.</li>
            <li>I occasionally make mistakes, so undo and redo are very helpful.</li>
            <li>I print.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>That&#8217;s about it. I know that there&#8217;s a ton of other features within MS Excel, but I want to simplify the requirements and fit those requirements into a smaller screen.</p>
            <p>With these requirements in mind, I put together a design mockup using Balsamiq. The primary screen is shown below. The majority of the screen is dedicated to the document itself, the table. I put an action bar across the top for common actions, and a row beneath that to edit a cell directly. It may be possible to remove this row and edit the cell contents in place, but that would have a significant impact on cell selection. I won&#8217;t go into it here.</p>
            <p><a href="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/03/spreadsheet-screen.png"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-466" title="spreadsheet-screen" src="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/03/spreadsheet-screen.png?w=595" alt=""   /></a></p>
            <p>The action bar structure is designed to emphasize the most common actions first. The cut, copy and paste actions are front and center. I put a file menu on the right to reflect the fact that it may be used when occasionally, but it&#8217;s not compulsory. If you make a change to the document it is saved immediately.</p>
            <p>The interaction with the table is more challenging.  If you want to change an item, just tap it. If you want to move it, tap it and then drag it. This is simple.  It&#8217;s a little more difficult to select multiple items. If you swipe the screen the document will scroll.  This is a common interaction pattern on a touch screen, and scrolling is critical in larger documents, so I have given it the priority. If you want to select multiple items you have to tap the first item. At this point a set of handles will appear beside it.  If you tap and drag one of these you can add adjacent items to the selection.</p>
            <p>The action menus are shown below. The most interesting one is the Cell menu. I decided to experiment within this menu by using a mix of column and grid layout.</p>
            <p><a href="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/03/spreadsheet-actions.png"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-467" title="spreadsheet-actions" src="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/03/spreadsheet-actions.png?w=595" alt=""   /></a></p>
            <p>I did not add a zoom function, but this could be supported using a pinch and stretch gesture.</p>
            <p>The end result is functional, but I&#8217;m not entirely satisfied with it. There are two thoughts in my head:</p>
            <ul>
            <li>A tablet app should deliver a very rich visual experience.  This is a rough mockup. I&#8217;d like to work with a visual designer to take it further.</li>
            <li>During the design process I chose to preserve the basic information architecture and feature set found within MS Excel. This is fine, but it would be even more interesting to develop a new paradigm for this space. In order to do that, I would have to step back, analyse the user goals, and develop a number of new, experimental solutions to achieve those goals.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>I may look at that in the future.</p>
            <br />  <a rel="nofollow" href="http://feeds.wordpress.com/1.0/gocomments/multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/448/"><img alt="" border="0" src="http://feeds.wordpress.com/1.0/comments/multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/448/" /></a> <img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=multitouchdesign.wordpress.com&#038;blog=20536839&#038;post=448&#038;subd=multitouchdesign&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/03/31/redesigning-ms-excel-for-a-tablet/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
            <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
            
            <media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/baaf3b5c536257b9132f368c3694a2b9?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">sprnggy</media:title>
            </media:content>
            
            <media:content url="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/03/spreadsheet-screen.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">spreadsheet-screen</media:title>
            </media:content>
            
            <media:content url="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/03/spreadsheet-actions.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">spreadsheet-actions</media:title>
            </media:content>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Smartphone App Developers v Sales</title>
            <link>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/03/24/smartphone-app-developers-v-sales/</link>
            <comments>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/03/24/smartphone-app-developers-v-sales/#comments</comments>
            <pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2012 10:20:37 +0000</pubDate>
            <dc:creator>David Springgay</dc:creator>
            <category><![CDATA[Development]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[development smartphone android iOS]]></category>
            
            <guid isPermaLink="false">http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/?p=412</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[Here&#8217;s a very interesting article from the Guardian on smartphone app developers, smartphone sales, and the intersection between them: Why aren&#8217;t smartphone app developers going where the sales are? Enjoy. Dave<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=multitouchdesign.wordpress.com&#038;blog=20536839&#038;post=412&#038;subd=multitouchdesign&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here&#8217;s a very interesting article from the Guardian on smartphone app developers, smartphone sales, and the intersection between them:</p>
            <p><a title="App Developers" href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/appsblog/2011/nov/18/smartphone-app-developers-sales">Why aren&#8217;t smartphone app developers going where the sales are?</a></p>
            <p>Enjoy.</p>
            <p>Dave</p>
            <br />  <a rel="nofollow" href="http://feeds.wordpress.com/1.0/gocomments/multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/412/"><img alt="" border="0" src="http://feeds.wordpress.com/1.0/comments/multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/412/" /></a> <img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=multitouchdesign.wordpress.com&#038;blog=20536839&#038;post=412&#038;subd=multitouchdesign&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/03/24/smartphone-app-developers-v-sales/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
            <slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
            
            <media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/baaf3b5c536257b9132f368c3694a2b9?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">sprnggy</media:title>
            </media:content>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Life in the Post PC world</title>
            <link>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/03/21/life-in-the-post-pc-world/</link>
            <comments>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/03/21/life-in-the-post-pc-world/#comments</comments>
            <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2012 22:37:46 +0000</pubDate>
            <dc:creator>David Springgay</dc:creator>
            <category><![CDATA[Future]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Interaction]]></category>
            
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/?p=432</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[As the sales of tablet computers continues to rage, I can&#8217;t help but wonder what the digital world will be like in a few years.  We all have more digital devices than ever before, and the personal computer is becoming a marginal device.  As this occurs, it`s a great time to step back and think [...]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=multitouchdesign.wordpress.com&#038;blog=20536839&#038;post=432&#038;subd=multitouchdesign&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As the sales of tablet computers continues to rage, I can&#8217;t help but wonder what the digital world will be like in a few years.  We all have more digital devices than ever before, and the personal computer is becoming a marginal device.  As this occurs, it`s a great time to step back and think about what makes each device good for some things, and less good for others.</p>
            <p>I have an iPod shuffle for running, an HTC phone for communication, an e-reader, a Android tablet for everyday use, a laptop at work, and a personal computer for heavy data entry.</p>
            <p>The shuffle is great when I want to consume information on a run. It&#8217;s so light that I don&#8217;t even notice it.  During a run my eyes and hands are busy, but my ears are free, so the headphones are a great source of audio entertainment.  It doesn&#8217;t have a visual interface, but I can live with that because it&#8217;s a single purpose device.  I just wish it had a voice interface that I could use to search for a song or podcast.</p>
            <p>The phone is also a great source of audio entertainment, but the fact that i can make phone calls from almost anywhere and interact with information on a screen turns it into a portable, connected computer.  The touch screen on most modern devices makes the interaction really good.  And systems like Siri on the iPhone have the potential to streamline interaction even more.  The on screen keyboard is a bit small, and there are a lot of times where I wish the screen was larger.  I wonder if it could be paired with direct display on or near the human eye.  Perhaps it will be <a title="Brain implants" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brain_implant">embedded inside the human head</a>.</p>
            <p><a href="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/03/mems-brain-implant-2.jpg"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-442" title="MEMS brain implant 2" src="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/03/mems-brain-implant-2.jpg?w=595" alt=""   /></a></p>
            <p>A tablet computer is a good fit when you want a larger screen and portability.  I think the popularity of the iPad is also a good indication that you don&#8217;t always need a mouse and keyboard. This is a very visual, tactile device.  Its a real pleasure to use.  It&#8217;s also really educational to see what happens when you port a mobile app to a tablet.  They often look sparse and fail to leverage the screen real estate.  Desktop apps do equally bad.  The controls are often too small to tap or read.  My finger isn&#8217;t a very precise pointing device.</p>
            <p>Stepping back, the iPad and its competitors have an entirely new interface, and the fact that these devices are so popular is having a profound effect on app design.  Traditional apps will be redesigned to work well on tablets, and new apps will emerge.</p>
            <p>What about the e- reader?  This is another single purpose device. It&#8217;s a great replacement for the book, which is very entertaining, and I can get hundreds of books into the space of a light weight e- reader.  That&#8217;s cool.  I&#8217;d also rather take my reader on the underground.  The tablet is too big, too fragile and too attractive to thieves.</p>
            <p>Then there&#8217;s my laptop.  I use a laptop at work for programming.  It has a great keyboard so I can blast stuff in, and it&#8217;s easy to move from place to place.  But the screen is small, so I have a large monitor on my desk which I plug it into.  I think that light, portable devices like this have a future.</p>
            <p><a href="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/03/macbook_air_thin_computer.jpg"><img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-437" title="macbook_air_thin_computer" src="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/03/macbook_air_thin_computer.jpg?w=300&#038;h=201" alt="" width="300" height="201" /></a></p>
            <p>That just leaves the traditional PC.  Its a great device when you need to do heavy data entry or analysis (think programming, financial trading, or computer aided design), but it&#8217;s not portable. In fact, it&#8217;s a white elephant.  These will disappear in favour of tablet and laptop computers.</p>
            <p>The fact that I have so many devices is frustrating because I have to manage them all individually, but this is short term issue.  The Apple iCloud and other similar solutions will help to bridge the gaps.</p>
            <p>As the popularity of tablets grow, more and more PC apps will be redesigned for the tablet, leading to greater marginalization of the PC.  What&#8217;s going to happen to Microsoft when Apple sells more devices than any other company?  I think the tables are turning.  Microsoft led in the 90s, but now it&#8217;s Apples turn.</p>
            <br />  <a rel="nofollow" href="http://feeds.wordpress.com/1.0/gocomments/multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/432/"><img alt="" border="0" src="http://feeds.wordpress.com/1.0/comments/multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/432/" /></a> <img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=multitouchdesign.wordpress.com&#038;blog=20536839&#038;post=432&#038;subd=multitouchdesign&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/03/21/life-in-the-post-pc-world/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
            <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
            
            <media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/baaf3b5c536257b9132f368c3694a2b9?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">sprnggy</media:title>
            </media:content>
            
            <media:content url="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/03/mems-brain-implant-2.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">MEMS brain implant 2</media:title>
            </media:content>
            
            <media:content url="http://multitouchdesign.files.wordpress.com/2012/03/macbook_air_thin_computer.jpg?w=300" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">macbook_air_thin_computer</media:title>
            </media:content>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Request and Download Patterns</title>
            <link>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/03/20/request-and-download-patterns/</link>
            <comments>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/03/20/request-and-download-patterns/#comments</comments>
            <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2012 23:45:33 +0000</pubDate>
            <dc:creator>David Springgay</dc:creator>
            <category><![CDATA[mobile web]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Patterns]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[downloaders]]></category>
            
            <guid isPermaLink="false">http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/?p=420</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[In my last post I blogged about the new WIFI system that Transport for London plans to install in the London Underground. This inspired me to think about mobile request and download patterns. It seems like there are two ways to download data. In the foreground, while the user waits, or in the background, when [...]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=multitouchdesign.wordpress.com&#038;blog=20536839&#038;post=420&#038;subd=multitouchdesign&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In my last post I blogged about the new WIFI system that Transport for London plans to install in the London Underground. This inspired me to think about mobile request and download patterns. It seems like there are two ways to download data. In the foreground, while the user waits, or in the background, when the network is available and connected.</p>
            <p><strong>In the Foreground</strong></p>
            <p>In a foreground download the download occurs directly in front of the user.  They watch it progress and have to wait until it completes before they can proceed.</p>
            <p>For instance, in a web browser the search function is critical. If you enter a search term and tap the search button, an http request is made with the search parameters. I understand that this should be done in a background thread, but to the user this will look like a foreground request. They&#8217;ll watch it run and long for it to complete because they want to see the results immediately.</p>
            <p>If a connection issue occurs during a foreground download, the download fails quickly.  This is useful feedback for the user, because there&#8217;s really no way to fulfill the request.  If the user really wants to do a search they can press the refresh button.</p>
            <p>This is a good approach when the amount of data which will be downloaded is small and can be downloaded quickly.</p>
            <p><strong>In the Background</strong></p>
            <p>In a background download, the download starts in the foreground but then fades to into the background while it proceeds.  This informs or encourages the user to do something else while they wait.</p>
            <p>For instance, in Google Play the search function is used to find the application you want. Once you find an application you need to download it. It can take anywhere from 30 seconds to 5 minutes to do this download, so the download is performed in the background. The user can watch the download progress in a small progress bar on the screen, search for another application, or switch to another task.</p>
            <p>If the network connection is lost for a few seconds or a few minutes it doesn&#8217;t matter.   The downloader will wait until the network is reconnected and continue the download.  It&#8217;s robust, and when the download is complete the user will be notified with an alert dialog or message.  If the download takes too long the user can cancel the request.</p>
            <p>This is a good approach when the amount of data which will be download is large, and it will take a long time to download.</p>
            <p><strong>Stepping Background</strong></p>
            <p>There are a couple of subjective elements in this discussion. How long can you ask the user to wait for a foreground download to complete? According to <a href="http://www.useit.com/papers/responsetime.html">Jakob Nielson</a>, the average user will wait 10 seconds before their attention starts to wander.  After that, you should use a progress bar to indicate how much longer they have to wait.  But on a mobile phone 10 seconds is a long time to wait, especially when your friends are waiting for you to show them how cool your app is.  If it takes more than 10 seconds to do a download, maybe you should do it in the background.</p>
            <p>The real time required to do a download also depends on whether your users typically connect using WIFI or 3G. If it takes a long time to download the data which is needed while connected to WIFI, it will take even longer on 3G. If your users are typically out and about, they may always be on 3G. In this situation it is really important to analyze and optimise the downloader or do the download in the background.</p>
            <p><strong>In Chunks</strong></p>
            <p>There&#8217;s one other technique worth considering.  If you can download data incrementally, it may be possible to show your user a taste of data while you download the rest.  This reduces the time required to wait, and can improve the user experience in your favor.</p>
            <br />  <a rel="nofollow" href="http://feeds.wordpress.com/1.0/gocomments/multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/420/"><img alt="" border="0" src="http://feeds.wordpress.com/1.0/comments/multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/420/" /></a> <img alt="" border="0" src="http://stats.wordpress.com/b.gif?host=multitouchdesign.wordpress.com&#038;blog=20536839&#038;post=420&#038;subd=multitouchdesign&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://multitouchdesign.wordpress.com/2012/03/20/request-and-download-patterns/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
            <slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
            
            <media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/baaf3b5c536257b9132f368c3694a2b9?s=96&#38;d=identicon&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">sprnggy</media:title>
            </media:content>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
